So if today's דף daf is מ"ח, Mem Chet, we pick up
מ"ז עמוד ב'. Mem Zayin amud bet. We have a lot to
do. We're on the about 10 lines down in the wide lines.
משרבו הרוצחנים, mishe'rabu harotzchanim, when the murderers increased, they stopped doing עגלה
ערופה. egla arufa. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, משרבו הרוצחנים בטלה עגלה ערופה
לפי שאינה באה אלא על הספק. mishe'rabu harotzchanim batla egla arufa lefi
she'eina ba'a ela al hasafek. It was only because of doubt, משרבו
הרוצחנים בגלוי mishe'rabu harotzchanim begaluy and once people were murdering out in
the open and nobody was without with impunity and people knew who
the murderers were, בטלה עגלה ערופה batla egla arufa they stopped doing
it. Again, I assume the point being that even if they knew
who
the in a particular case they didn't know who it was, it
was a type of a of a society in which it made
no sense to take outrage and to take responsibility for when it
was not known if people were doing it publicly and getting away
with it. משרבו הנואפים, mishe'rabu hano'afim, when the adulterers increased, they stopped
doing סוטה, sota, tying us back to the major theme of the
מסכת. masechet. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, ונקתה האשה מעון בזמן שהאיש מנוקה
מעון, venizka ha'isha me'avon bizman she'ish menuke me'avon, המים בודקין את אשתו.
hamayim bodkin et ishto. When the man is clean from sin, the
water test tests his wife. אין איש מנוקה מעון אין המים בודקין
את אשתו. ein ish menuke me'avon ein hamayim bodkin et ishto. Not
when he's not clean from sin. Interestingly, when we did this earlier,
the idea was that when he violated specifically the laws of סוטה
sota and slept with his wife when she was a סוטה, sota,
but here we are broadening it really to any type of a
sin, okay? ואומר, ve'omer, and it says,
לא אפקוד על בנותיכם כי תזנינה, lo efkod al benoseichem ki tiznena,
I will not visit upon your daughters when they when they, you
know, fornicate, because you are running after prostitutes, the end of the
verse. מאי ואומר, mai ve'omer, what does that mean? וכי תימא עון
דידיה אין דבני ובנותיו לא, vechitayma avon didei in dibnei ubenosei lo,
maybe only his sexual sin is when the waters don't work, but
if it's his daughter's, son or daughter's, no? תא שמע לא אפקוד
על בנותיכם כי תזנינה ועל כלותיכם כי תנאפנה. tashma lo efkod al
benoseichem ki tiznena ve'al kaloseichem ki tena'afena. Okay, I won't visit, so
presumably here too reading it I won't visit on your daughters when
they sin for their sexual sin, but I won't visit the sin
if you allow your daughters and because you allow your daughters and
your daughters-in-law to commit sexual sins. So you are held responsible even
for their sexual sins. Again, I don't know if we're saying that
as a quote-unquote הלכתית halakhic point, you know, in terms of issues
discussed earlier, but certainly here in the broad societal sense. וכי תימא
עון אשת איש אין עון דפנויה לא, vechitayma avon eshet ish in
avon depnuya lo, maybe that's only if somebody
violates the prohibition of adultery, but not just like general sexual immorality
like you know or whatever, any sexual sin if the woman is
not married. תא שמע כי הם עם הזונות יפרדו, tashma ki heim
im hazonot yepareidu, they will sleep with the with the prostitutes, so
that's not a that's just, you know, general sexual violation, it is
not a sin of of adultery and nevertheless that's why the סוטה
sota is no longer working. ועם הקדשות יזבחו, ve'im hakedeshot yizabei'chu, and
with the cult sacrifice prostitutes they will offer sacrifice. מאי ועם לא
יבין ילבט, mai ve'am lo yavin yilabet, and
a nation that doesn't understand ילבט. yilabet. So again, what does that
word mean? So it probably means like will grow weary. אמר רבי
אמר אמר רבי אלעזר אמר להם הנביא לישראל, amar Rabbi amar amar
Rabbi Elazar amar lahem ha'navi le'Yisrael, the prophet says to ישראל, Yisrael,
אם אתם מקפידים על עצמכם, im atem makpidim al atzmechem, if you
are careful on yourselves and you know about your own behavior, מים
בודקין את נשיכם, mayim bodkin et nesheichem, ואם לאו אין המים בודקין
את נשיכם. ve'im lav ein hamayim bodkin et nesheichem. And if not,
it will not. I'm not sure how we get that from the
word ילבט, yilabet, but anyway. By the way, I should also say
that רש"י Rashi says the meaning of the word יפרדו yepareidu is
like a פרד, pered, like a what's a פרד? pered? A mule,
like you know, basically means just fornicate regularly.
Are these זונות וקדשות? zonot ve'kedeshot?
Yes, I said קדשות kedeshot are cult prostitutes. Cult, C-U-L-T, yeah. Okay,
so all right, I'm not sure exactly how they're getting that from
ילבט. yilabet. Okay, anyway, moving on.
Okay. משרבו בעלי הנאה, mishe'rabu ba'alei hana'ah, now we're going to get
to a general way about how society has all gone to pot
and the different types of problems. So when people who are too
much indulging in pleasure, now this does not mean hedonism, basically according
to רש"י Rashi it just means you know people that want to
just relax a little bit too much, aren't were you know don't
really believe in like you know just hard work.
So נתעוות הדינים, nit'avu hadinim, the justice or you know the laws
what I mean the the judgments were perverted because the judges who
wants to work so hard and putting in all that effort to
really investigate a case and so on? You know, you take life
a little easy, so that perverts justice. ונתקלקלו המעשים, venitkalkelu hama'asim, and
actions are corrupted because then people feel that they can get away
with things. ואין נוח בעולם, ve'ein no'ach ba'olam, and there's no pleasantness
in the world, רש"י Rashi says it means that God does not
take pleasure in the world
because משרבו רואי פנים בדין, mishe'rabu roei panim badin, once people who
showed favor to in justice in
in judgment, which doesn't necessarily mean blatant bribes, but nevertheless, you know,
you know showed favor to people that they knew, so or even
just to acknowledge them, you know, and did not were not completely
impartial in their behavior. So in that case בטלה לא תגורו מפני
איש, batla lo taguru mipnei ish, so it stopped the idea of
fearing from people. Obviously they were then responsive to who the litigants
were. ופסק לא תכירו u'pasak lo takiru and it ended do not
recognize people—I mean I should have started with that, that's the whole
point is that you're recognizing who the litigants are—ופרקו עול שמים u'parku
ol shamayim ונתנו
עליהם עול בשר ודם venatnu aleihem ol basar vadam and this presumably
means from the justices they cast off the yoke of heaven and
they put upon themselves the yoke of בשר ודם basar vadam because
now they are influenced by who are the people in front of
them and that's having more of an impact than the fact that
they're doing דין שמים, din shamayim, you know, and they have to
answer to God. משרבו לוחשי לחישות בדין mishe'rabu lochashei lechishot b'din it's
so interesting that all the interesting things start with justice, you know,
because that ultimately if the court and the justice system is in
place, that's what keeps everybody, that sends the biggest message to society
both in terms of practically it keeps people in place and also
like, you know, what it represents for society.
גסי הרוח, gasei haruach, this idea of about
the yoke of heaven for the yoke of בשר ודם. basar vadam.
Right.
So, okay, so when people did whispered incantations in judgment, presumably they
felt that that was a way to, you know, that they were
going to influence the outcome because of some types of incantations. אורחי
דיינים. orchei dayanim.
אורחי דיינים, orchei dayanim, oh, good point. Oh, so lawyers, I missed
that Rashi. Okay, so they whispered to the—מתלחשים עם הדיינים לפתוח להם
פתח בזכות, mitlachashim im hadayanim liftuach lahem petach bizchut, oh, that's a
good point, they whispered in the ear of the judges. Oh, that's
a very good point, I missed that. Okay, you're called to say
lawyers are whispering to the litigants. Okay, so when whisperers increased in
the court, רבה חרון אף בישראל, raba charon af b'Yisrael, anger amongst
the Jewish people increased, ונסתלקה שכינה, venistalka Shechinah,
and the divine presence removed, משום שנאמר בקרב אלוהים ישפוט, mishum shene'emar
b'kerev Elohim yishpot,
that judgment is in the presence of God and here God is
being sort of removed from it. So, משרבו אחרי בצעם לבם הולך,
mishe'rabu acharei bitzam libam holech, after,
you know, gain their hearts go, רבו האומרים לרע טוב ולטוב רע,
rabu ha'omrim lara tov velatov ra, so everybody was just, you know,
everybody was focused on profit and making money. So therefore, רבו האומרים
לרע טוב ולטוב רע, rabu ha'omrim lara tov velatov ra, people would
say about bad is good, good is bad, people would just flatter
people, they would no longer be any truth, people would tell people
what they needed to to get ahead. And משרבו האומרים לרע טוב
ולטוב רע, mishe'rabu ha'omrim lara tov velatov ra, רבו הוי הוי בעולם,
rabu hoy hoy ba'olam, woe woe to the world which is the
end of the pasuk, which is later in those pesukim it says
a lot in that section in the Navi. משרבו מושכי הרוק, mishe'rabu
moshchei harok, when people who drew their spit increased, which is a
type of an act of haughtiness, you know, I don't know, maybe
you speak very slowly or something like that, you know, an act
of—anyway, רבו היהירים, rabu hayehirim,
so increase those who are—take on airs, ונתמעטו התלמידים, venitma'atu hatalmidim,
and there was less—and the Torah sage students decreased because if every—Rashi
says what's that about? Rashi says just דקיימא לן סימן לגסות הרוח
עניות של תורה. dekayma lan siman legasut haruach aniyut shel Torah.
Okay,
I don't know if people are taking on airs without earning it
maybe or something, anyway, you know, people aren't working hard enough to
learn Torah, I'm not exactly sure about the connection there,
but maybe again people are focusing on the externals rather than on
the real types of learning that is required, והתורה חוזרת על לומדיה,
vehaTorah chozeret al lomdeha,
and the Torah is looking around for somebody to learn it, for
somebody who's really going to invest in it as is necessary. משרבו
היהירים, mishe'rabu hayehirim, and once those with airs, the haughty increased, התחילו
בנות ישראל להינשא ליהירים, hitchilu bnot Yisrael lehinase layehirim, so then people
would marry—the daughters, the women would marry the people that looked, you
know, that had these airs even though they were not really genuine,
שאין דורנו רואה אלא לפנים, she'ein dorenu ro'eh ela lifnim,
because our generation only sees the externals, does not really see whether
somebody has really earned the status that they're presenting themselves with.
It's the author of the Tosefta, I think this is all big
Tosefta. איני, eini, is this really true? והאמר מר, veha'amar mar, and
now finally the Gemara speaks up. והאמר מר האי מאן דמיהיר אפילו
אינש ביתיה לא מקבלי ליה, veha'amar mar hai man demayahir afilu inish
beiteih lo mikabli leih, somebody that is haughty
even his members of his household have no tolerance for him. So
how is it that women are attracted to such a guy? שנאמר
גבר יהיר ולא ינוה, shene'emar gever yahir velo yanveh, a man will
act haughty and will not be means like dwell, לא ינוה אפילו
בנוה שלו, lo yanveh afilu b'naveh shelo,
he can't even dwell in his own house because his house maybe
sees through his act and has no—and doesn't tolerate him. So the
Gemara says מעיקרא קפצה ליה, me'ikara kaftza leih, no, originally he, you
know, before you get to know him too well, everybody wants to
marry him because he looks like a חשוב chashuv person, ולבסוף מיצלא
ליה, ulevasof mitzla leih,
but then once they get married and the wife gets to know
who her husband is, then he becomes lowly in her eyes. Okay.
משרבו מטילי מלאי על בעלי בתים, mishe'rabu matilei melai al ba'alei batim,
once the people started, the dayanim started, you know, having their money
invested
with businessmen, so the businessmen would say, oh, do you a favor,
give me your money, I'll invest it to—you know, I'll invest it
for you. What?
New financial guys or brokers?
Yeah, exactly. Well, the problem here is is that if the dayanim
are in, you know, it's not in some anonymous,
what do you call it, fund, it's
particular businessmen... particular businessmen are offering to invest their money for them.
So רבה השוחד, raba hashochar, obviously, increased bribery, because obviously it
was continuing that was just spoke about.
Yes, exactly. Okay, רבה השוחד raba hashochar והטיית משפט v'hatayas mishpat and
the perversion of justice, the
or the inclination of justice, ופסקה טובה v'paska tova and all good
ended. It's very all these different things about different ways in which
the particularly justice has been perverted, you know, and the judges. משרבו
מקבלני טובתך ומחזיקי טובתייך mishe-rabu mekablei tovascha u-machzikei tovasayich when it increased
the people that said, "Oh, yeah, thank you very much for that
favor," you know, "and I'm very grateful for you to the favor
you did for me." Again, this is a way judges would relate
to people in the community. So they would acknowledge, you know, accept
favors and acknowledge them and so on. רבו איש הישר בעיניו יעשה
rabu ish ha-yashar be-einav ya'aseh then anybody could get away with anything.
Because, you know, then the judges would be in, would be indebted
to you. שפלים הוגבהו והגבוהים הושפלו shfalim hugbehu v'hagvohim hushpelu the low
were raised up, the high were brought down, ומלכותא אזלא ונבלא u-malchusa
azla v'navla and the and the whole, you know, the whole government
is going to pot. Yes, that's a rough translation.
Yes, interestingly, the judge there said at the beginning, she introduced herself,
she said, "I'm not going to be able to say hello to
you.
Don't take it as a personal thing," yeah, because they're not allowed
to. Really? Interesting. Nice, nice.
Well, actually this is what we're going through right now in terms
of legislators, making it a part-time legislature, which basically means they have
to seek outside work in New York. And it's led to all
these corruption trials. Interesting, right, right. This is very, I guess, topical
in the last month.
Okay. משרבו צרי עין mishe-rabu tsarei ayin when it increased those who
were of stingy, וטורפי טרף v'torfei teref and those who would literally
like take, you know, a what is it, you know, a grabbings,
I don't know exactly how that's connected to צרי עין. tsarei ayin.
רש"י Rashi says just גזלנים. gazlanim. Okay. Not exactly sure how that's
connected. Oh, well I guess it's people that are just very, you
know, only care about money. So either they they don't give of
their money to others or they just whatever, they're willing to take
other people's money.
רבו מאמיצי הלב rabu ma'amitsei ha-lev those hard of heart, not generous.
It's interesting because that doesn't seem so causal, that might the causation
goes in the other direction. Anyway, וקופצי הידיים v'kofsei ha-yadayim and those
that that, you know, close up their hands from lending money, ועברו
על מה שכתוב בתורה השמר לך פן יהיה עם לבבך v'avru al
mah she-kasuv ba-Torah hishamer lecha pen yihyeh im levavcha right be be
careful that you do not have this feeling that why should I
give money to somebody and lend money, especially with שמיטה Shmita coming
around the bend. משרבו נטויות גרון ומשקרות עיניים mishe-rabu netuyos garon u-meshakros
einayim
those of outstretched necks and, you know, and like beckoning eyes. רבו
rabu by people that are acting to attract the attention to themselves
and to act in a in a haughty manner.
Like on Yom Kippur.
Right, exactly. רבו rabu and also it's very sexual, like people who
are acting, presumably it's specifically relating here to women and acting in
ways in which to attract a man's attention.
So stretching out their necks to look and— Yeah, exactly, exactly.
And like using their eyes to beckon a man or something. רבו
מים המרים. rabu mayim ha-marim. So in theory what should have happened
is that the bitter water should have increased because there were all
these women who were potentially were suspected of straying around. אלא שפסקו
ela she-pasku except for the problem was was that it was so
prevalent, you know, not only with them, but with the men committing
adultery and so on, that we weren't doing the מים המרים mayim
ha-marim anymore. Okay. משרבו מקבלי מתנות mishe-rabu mekablei matanos
when people who received gifts increased, נתמעטו הימים nisma'atu ha-yamim the days
people... ונתקצרו השנים v'niskatseru ha-shanim
people live shorter lives. דכתיב ושונא מתנות יחיה. de-chasiv v'soneh matanos yichyeh.
Okay, only if you hate the gifts you will live. Interesting, right,
most of these are real like really practical, you know, and it's
interesting also when like a certain like
divine punishment is sort of brought in. Okay. משרבו זחוחי הלב mishe-rabu
zechuchei ha-lev when the people of haughtiness of heart or like, you
know, רבו מחלוקת בישראל rabu machlokes b'Yisrael
then there was much debate in Israel because then the students did
not devote all their energies to understanding what their rabbis were teaching
them, right, they were a little bit like taking things a little
too easy. משרבו תלמידי שמאי והלל שלא שמשו כל צרכן mishe-rabu talmidei
Shammai v'Hillel she-lo shimshu kol tsorkan
and this sort of like flies and falls into the next, when
the increase of students of Shammai and Hillel that did not devote
all of their effort to attending to their rabbis, so רבו מחלוקת
בישראל ונעשו תורה כשתי תורות rabu machlokes b'Yisrael v'na'asu Torah k'shtei Toros
there was much debate and was like two Toras because there was
now that's when there were all these מחלוקות machlokos debates; right until
that time there was very there was almost nothing of תורה שבעל
פה Torah she-ba'al peh that was debated.
משרבו מקבלי צדקה מעובדי כוכבים mishe-rabu mekablei tzedakah me-ovdei chochavim once people
began receiving charity from the from non-Jews, so היו ישראל למעלה והם
למטה hayu Yisrael l'ma'ala v'hem l'mata this is said לשון סגי נהור
lashon sagi nahor the reverse. Okay, they you know Israel were above
and they were below, it means the reverse. ישראל לפנים והם לאחור.
Yisrael l'fanim v'hem l'achor. Of course, again the funny thing is is
that which way does that causation go? Because they accepted charity? Or
maybe it was a they needed to accept charity because the general
fortunes had been reversed. Yes.
All the Frum websites are all excited when we get money from
the non-Jewish government.
There you go. Okay. משימת יוסי בן יועזר mishe-meis Yosi ben Yoezer
when Yosi ben Yoezer died,
בטלו האשכולות. batlu ha-eshkolos. מאי אשכול? mai eshkol? אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל איש שהכל בו amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel ish she-ha-kol bo
people that are all these fully complete תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and
again that ties into the last line we just said. before that
was the that was when the period of you know of until
that point there really had been no debates in תורה שבעל פה
Torah she-ba'al peh and after that point things were heavily heavily debated.
The מסורה, Mesorah, the unbroken מסורה Mesorah stopped. Or even if before
not everything was by מסורה, Mesorah, there was enough unanimity and consensus
that any issue would be agreed upon, and after that point there
were all those debates. יוחנן כהן גדול העביר הודית המעשר Yochanan Kohen
Gadol he'evir hodiyat ha-ma'aser and now we get to a little more
practical issues. יוחנן כהן גדול Yochanan Kohen Gadol stopped doing people confessing
or whatever about the מעשר Ma'aser when they would give the מעשר
Ma'aser after three years or whatever. If they had stored it up,
they would say that I've distributed it correctly; he brought an end
to that. Now why? I mean fitting into the theme you would
think well maybe because people enough people aren't doing it correctly that
it's absurd to be making this, but the גמרא Gemara actually gives
a different reason. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama on the last line of
מ"ז עמוד ב. Mem-zayin amud bet. What's the reason? אמר רבי יוסי
בר חנינא לפי שאינו נותנו כתיקונו. Amar Rabbi Yosei bar Chanina lefi
she-eino notno ke-tikkuno. Actually the reason is because not it's not one
of these ירידת הדורות Yeridat Ha-dorot problems; it's because people weren't giving
it in the right way. But not because they were doing anything
wrong. Why? דרחמנא אמר דיהבי ללוים. De-rachmana amar di-yavi le-Levi'im. The תורה
Torah says to give it to the לוים. Levi'im. ואנן יהבינן לכהנים,
Ve-anan yahavinan le-Kohanim, we give it to the כהנים. Kohanim. That had
to do with the fact that the לוים Levi'im did not return
in the time of עזרא, Ezra, so we made a קנס Kenas
and we didn't give it to the לוים; Levi'im; we gave it
to כהנים, Kohanim, who are לוים Levi'im so we actually were technically
doing what we needed to do but certainly not the basic point
of the תורה Torah and וגם נתתיו ללוי. Ve-gam netativ la-Levi. So
he said since it's not exactly the way the תורה Torah wants
us we cannot make this this statement because it really is not
exactly precise. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says but this by the
way I think the juxtaposition of this is quite fascinating, right? Until
this it was like how society is going to pot and here
actually a תקנה Takkanah of חז"ל Chazal sort of made us diverge
from this ideal that the תורה Torah had like set out. Of
course that was probably because the people had diverged because the לוים
Levi'im didn't return so it was all ultimately maybe going back to
larger problems in society.
Why wasn't it a temporary? Why wasn't that a temporary תקנה? Takkanah?
I don't I don't know. Yeah, I don't know. I mean, yeah,
I don't know.
This is 500 years earlier.
Right, it's right. And like well maybe that's the point. Look even
500 years earlier than all these events, you know, we start you
were starting to see a crack in the and you were starting
to see a crack in the edifice. Like we were already going
away from the perfect sort of way the תורה Torah had set
it out. Okay. ולא דיה שאר מעשרות. Ve-lo deiah she'ar ma'asrot. Why
not just skip וגם נתתיו ללוי Ve-gam netativ la-Levi and do the
whole and do the confession on the rest of the מעשרות? Ma'asrot?
אמר ריש לקיש כל בית שאין מתודה על מעשר ראשון שוב אין
מתודה על שאר מעשרות. Amar Reish Lakish kol bayit she-ein mitvaddeh al
ma'aser rishon shuv ein mitvaddeh al she'ar ma'asrot. If you can't do
the beginning opening statement, you can't do the rest. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? אמר אביי הואיל ופתח בו הכתוב תחילה Amar Abaye ho'il u-fatach
bo ha-katuv techilah because it starts with that
וגם נתתיו ללוי. Ve-gam netativ la-Levi. מכלל דאפרושי הוי מפרשי. Mi-klal de-afroshi
havei mafrishei. So it sounds like they were separating מעשרות Ma'asrot and
the only problem was was that they, you know again, they were
giving it to the
כהנים. Kohanim. והתניא אף הוא ביטל את הוידוי וגזר על הדמאי. Ve-ha
tanya af hu bittel et ha-viddui ve-gazar al ha-demai. One minute, but
we said that not only did he annul the וידוי, Viddui, he
also instituted that everybody should be מפריש Mafrish on the דמאי Demai
on grain that they bought from the עמי הארץ. Ammei Ha-aretz. לפי
Lefi why? Famous גמרא Gemara here for for because דמאי Demai comes
up a lot in the גמרא Gemara and this is like the
explanation of it. It's not the only place it appears; it's in
בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, it's a תוספתא. Tosefta. לפי ששלח בכל גבול
ישראל. Lefi she-shalach be-khol gevul Yisrael. He sent throughout all the borders
of Israel. וראה שאין מפרישין אלא תרומה גדולה בלבד. Ve-ra'ah she-ein mafrishin
ela terumah gedolah bilvad. And he saw that people that would only
take the, עמי הארץ Ammei Ha-aretz at least, would only take
תרומה גדולה. Terumah Gedolah. ומעשר ראשון ומעשר שני מקצתן מעשרין ומקצתן אין
מעשרין. U-ma'aser rishon u-ma'aser sheni miktzatan ma'asrin u-miktzatan ein ma'asrin. And as
far as מעשר ראשון, Ma'aser rishon, מעשר שני, Ma'aser sheni, some people
would and some people would not do it. אמר להם Amar lahem
because they figured look, תרומה גדולה Terumah Gedolah is like חייב מיתה
Chayyav mitah if you eat it and it's תרומה, Terumah, goes to
a כהן. Kohen. The other stuff, alright, we don't give the עני,
Ani, we don't give the לוי Levi what they deserve, big deal.
אמר להם בני בואו ואומר לכם. Amar lahem banai bo'u ve-omar lakhem.
He said to them, my children, come and let me tell you.
כשם שתרומה גדולה יש בה עון מיתה. Keshem she-terumah gedolah yesh bah
avon mitah. The same way there's a punishment of death by תרומה
גדולה Terumah Gedolah in heaven. כך תרומת מעשר וטבל יש בהן עון
מיתה. Kakh terumat ma'aser ve-tevel yesh bahen avon mitah. Same as תרומת
מעשר Terumat ma'aser and טבל, Tevel, the grain you have not taken
תרומת מעשר Terumat ma'aser from. So if you haven't taken מעשר, Ma'aser,
then you haven't taken
the תרומת מעשר Terumat ma'aser from the מעשר Ma'aser and the תרומת
מעשר Terumat ma'aser is still buried in your טבל Tevel and there's
still חיוב מיתה. Chiyyuv mitah. So therefore, you better be careful to
take that.
Is that really? Is that true?
No, it's true. Yes. Now wait, I mean that's the הלכה. Halacha.
We don't say that by if you haven't taken מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni or מעשר עני, Ma'aser Ani, but if you haven't taken מעשר
לוי, Ma'aser Levi, the טבל Tevel is still חייב מיתה Chiyyuv mitah
because of the
תרומת מעשר Terumat ma'aser שבו. she-bo. Okay, so
okay. Actually I'm looking at רש"י Rashi and it seems like רש"י
Rashi the question is who's he saying this to? Is he saying
this to the עמי הארץ Ammei Ha-aretz or is he saying this
to the חברים Chaverim who are buying from the עמי הארץ? Ammei
Ha-aretz? It seems like it's a little bit the latter and that
he's telling them that you're buying from the עמי הארץ Ammei Ha-aretz
and you're not worrying about this. You gotta worry about this because
if the עמי הארץ Ammei Ha-aretz didn't do it, you're still חייב
מעשר Chayyav ma'aser on this stuff. So
therefore אמר והתקין להם Amar ve-hitkin lahem and therefore right because that's
clear from the next line. The people he's talking to are not
the עמי הארץ, Ammei Ha-aretz, it's the people buying from the עמי
הארץ. Ammei Ha-aretz. So he got up and he established for them
הלוקח פירות מעמי הארץ, haloke'ach peirot me'amei ha'aretz, when you buy from
the עם הארץ, Am Haaretz, don't just assume eh, it's probably fine.
No. מפרישין מעשר ראשון ומעשר שני, mafrishin ma'aser rishon u'ma'aser sheni, you
have to, yes, they've taken the תרומה, terumah, but you have to
be concerned that they haven't taken the rest. So therefore, separate off
מעשר ראשון ומעשר שני. ma'aser rishon u'ma'aser sheni. מעשר ראשון, ma'aser rishon,
now what do you do with your מעשר ראשון? ma'aser rishon? מפריש
ממנו תרומת מעשר ונותנו לכהן, mafrish mimeno terumas ma'aser venosno lachohen, take
תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser and give that to the כהן. kohen. So
that'll wind up being basically 1% of what you just bought, 10%
of
10%. ומעשר שני u'ma'aser sheni goes up and you eat it in
ירושלים yerushalayim or redeem it. Now מעשר ראשון ומעשר עני, ma'aser rishon
u'ma'aser ani, the מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon that's left behind after the
תרומת מעשר, terumas ma'aser, or if it's the third and the sixth
year and you have מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, so in that case
המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. That's not a question
of any קדושה, kedusha, that's just a question of being owned by
the לוי levi or owned by the עני. ani. So they have
the burden of proof that it's theirs because maybe actually the עם
הארץ Am Haaretz actually took it before you bought it, so you're
allowed to keep it. So in the end the impact on you
is relatively minor. Fine. Anyway, so he established דמאי demai that anything
you buy from the עם הארץ Am Haaretz you have to be
concerned it didn't have everything taken from it, you have to take
the rest of the תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'ma'asros. So anyway the question
is, so it sounds
like was it that everybody was doing all the הפרשה hafrasha they
needed and they just he just spoke about the וידוי, viduy, or
did he have to establish that even did the necessary הפרשה? hafrasha?
You know what's so the גמרא gemara says, why not both? So
the גמרא gemara says תרתי תקין, tertei tikin, he established two things:
ביטל וידוי דחברים. bitel viduy d'chaverim. Number one, even on your own
grain that you are taking everything off of because it's your own
grain, so you know that you're חייב, chayav, you separate everything, so
you would think you could do the וידוי viduy because you've separated
everything? No, you can't do the וידוי. viduy. And on the grain
you buy from the עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz, which you until this
point has not been doing the
הפרשה, hafrasha, וגזר דמאי של עמי הארץ, vegazar demai shel amei ha'aretz,
you have to start taking the stuff from the עמי הארץ. amei
ha'aretz. Okay. ואף הוא ביטל את המעוררים. ve'af hu bitel es hame'orerim.
He also he also brought an end to the wake-upers and the
bangers. So what is that? מאי מעוררים? mai me'orerim? אמר רחבה בכל
יום ויום שהיו עומדים לוים על הדוכן ואומרים, amar rechava bechol yom
vayom shehayu omdim levi'im al haduchan ve'omrim, because it used to be
every day the לוים levi'im would get up on the דוכן duchan
and they would say before they would do their singing, עורה למה
תישן ה׳. urah lamah tishan hashem. Wake up! Why would you sleep
oh God? So אמר להם, amar lahem, this is a pretty funny
thing to say in the morning. Seems very pagan right? Wake up
God? וכי יש שינה לפני המקום? vechi yesh sheinah lifnei hamakom? Is
there sleep before God? והלא כבר נאמר הנה לא ינום ולא יישן
שומר ישראל, vahalo kvar neemar hinei lo yanum velo yishan shomer yisrael,
אלא בזמן שישראל שרויים בצער ela bizman sheyisrael sheruyim betza'ar ועובדי כוכבים
בנחת ושלוה, ve'ovdei kochavim benachas veshalvah,
metaphorically when we have anguish and the non-Jews have it all good,
so therefore we're saying לכך נאמר עורה למה תישן, lechach neemar urah
lamah tishan, God how could you allow this to continue? But that's
not a thing that you say in the first thing in the
בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. It's very strange. I mean you certainly understand
why he was מבטל mevatel it. You'd like to know how this
ever got started right? It does sound pretty pagan. Okay. I
know. But the fact that he responds and saying it's metaphorical means
that they were assuming that it was a little bit more literal
right? And why would they be saying that? I mean it was
in the middle of the time of the second בית המקדש. beis
hamikdash. It wasn't a tragic time necessarily right? He wasn't saying oh
it is metaphorical but it doesn't sound good. He says stop saying
it, it's only a metaphor. Right? So it sounds like anyway it
is pretty disturbing. ואת הנוקפים. ve'es hanokfim. The bangers. Who are the
bangers? מאי נוקפים? mai nokfim? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל שהיו מסרטין
לעגל בין קרניו amar rav yehuda amar shmuel shehayu mesartin le'egel bein
karnav כדי שיפול דם בעיניו, kedei sheyipol dam be'einav, where they had
to slaughter an animal in the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. So this
was like they would make a they would scratch like a scratch
between the eyes and there would blood would run into the eyes
and it would sort of confuse the animal and they would be
able to שחט shacht it without it getting too
upset. Okay. Okay. ואתא איהו ובטיל, ve'asa ihu uvatil, he annulled that
משום דמיחזי כבעל מום, mishum demechazi kiba'al mum, it looks like a
blemish. במתניתא תנא, bemasnisa tana, in a ברייתא braisa we taught שהיו
חובטים אותו במקלות, shehayu chovtin oso bemaklos, they would actually this is
like before stunning, they would hit it with sticks כדרך שעושין אותו
לפני עובדי כוכבים. kederech she'osin oso lifnei ovdei kochavim. And again by
the way notice before the other thing which has a problem of
a מום, mum, this is a similar problem that it looks a
little pagan. Okay, so that'll what they would do in you know
in pagan worship. Okay. I don't know why they would do it
in pagan worship but anyway they would bang it with sticks to
stun it and then they would slaughter it. But he didn't like
that. Okay. אמר להם amar lahem עד מתי אתם מאכילים נבילות למזבח?
ad masai atem ma'achilim neveilos lamizbeach? Now again it's an interesting transition.
It mentioned like they would do in pagan worship which seems to
connect to the earlier problem. But then it emphasizes that the problem
is that you're making it not kosher, you're making it
טריפה. treifa. So the גמרא gemara says נבילות? neveilos? השחוט לעזרה קא
תני נבילה? hashachut la'azarah ka tani neveila? נבילה neveila is an animal
that isn't שחט. shechted. This was שחט. shechted. אלא טריפות. ela tereifos.
No you're making it a possible טריפה treifa by hitting it. שמא
ניקב קרום של מוח. shema nikev krum shel moach. Maybe you're getting
making a hole in the you know in the thing the in
the brain whatever that is what's that thing in the brain. Anyway.
עמד והתקין להם טבעות בקרקע. amad vehitkin lahem tabaos bakarka. So he
said if you want to keep your animals steady and not to
thrash around when you're שחט shechting them, he put these rings in
the ground and they stick their heads through the rings. Okay. ועד
ימיו היה פטיש מכה בירושלים, ve'ad yamav hayah patish makeh biyerushalayim, they
would have the hammer in the... Of the a blacksmith
place in ירושלים Yerushalayim because of דבר האבד, devar ha'avad, but he
ended that because that was very public and loud and it sent
a message that people could do work on חול המועד Chol HaMoed
that they on חול המועד Chol HaMoed they used to allow this,
בחולו של מועד becholoh shel Moed as the גמרא Gemara says. כל
המביא דמאי צריך לשאול על הדמאי, Kol hamavi demai tzarich lishol al
hademai, nobody had to ask about the דמאי demai כי דאמרינן k'de'amrinan
as we said because now everybody was מפריש mafrish on the דמאי
demai so you no longer had to worry about it, you would
just always take. Okay. Next משנה. mishna. משבטלה סנהדרין בטל השיר מבית
המשתאות. Mishebatlah Sanhedrin batel hashir mibeit hamishtaot. Once there was no longer
a סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, they stopped singing in the drinking houses, שנאמר בשיר
לא ישתו יין. shene'emar bashir lo yishtu yayin. Now what does that
have to do with the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? We will see. But also
very strange, right? I mean I guess it means like joy ceased,
right? If you would normally assume like would you assume the חז"ל
Chazal would be upset that they weren't singing in the drinking houses?
Doesn't say religious song, right? But maybe to some degree it just
means that joy ceased. But again, it's interesting connecting that. We normally
talk about like not singing and so on you know and live
music related to the חורבן בית המקדש. Churban Beit HaMikdash. Here it's
related to the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. But remember again that the whole theme
of the מסכת masechet and what we mentioned before, all this thing
about the דיינים, dayanim, right? Is about like you know law and
making sure that the society is running the way it needs to
and that there's clear you know true judges and the and you
know an even responsibility for issues of doubt like עגלה ערופה eglah
arufah and סוטה. Sotah. So it's very much tied in here to
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin more than the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
You see it like descriptive or prescriptive?
No, well that's true we also have a prescriptive idea about that
but this seems to be descriptive. Okay. משמתו נביאים ראשונים בטלו אורים
ותומים. Mishemetu nevi'im rishonim batlu urim vetumim. When the early prophets died,
we'll see who that's referring to, בטלו אורים ותומים batlu urim vetumim
ceased. Maybe its effectiveness ceased or the whole thing stopped. משחרב בית
המקדש. Mishecharav Beit HaMikdash. Now when the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was
destroyed, בטל השמיר. batel hashamir. The שמיר shamir which is that magic
worm that can crack stone, that got lost or ceased. ונופת צופים.
venofet tzufim. And what? Became extinct. Became extinct and the נופת צופים,
nofet tzufim, we'll see what that means. Some type of a sweetness
of, well we'll see what it means. ופסקו אנשי אמנה מישראל. v'pasku
anshei amanah miYisrael. And people of faith
ceased שנאמר הושיעה ה' כי גמר חסיד כי פסו אמונים מבני אדם.
shene'emar hoshi'ah Hashem ki gamar chasid ki
pasu emunim mibnei adam.
Right. פסו pasu or פסקו? pasku? פסו. pasu. Yes פסו. pasu. פסו.
pasu. Anyway. But because people of faith have ceased. Okay. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer. העיד רבי יהושע מיום
שחרב בית המקדש. He'id Rabbi Yehoshua miyom shecharav Beit HaMikdash. From the
time the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash ceased, אין יום שאין בו קללה.
ein yom she'ein bo klalah. There's no day that doesn't have an
element of curse in it. ולא ירד הטל לברכה. velo yarad hatal
livrachah. And the dew does not come down for blessing. וניטל טעם
הפירות. venital ta'am hapeirot. And even the taste of fruit has ceased.
רבי יוסי אומר אף ניטל שומן הפירות. Rabbi Yosi omer af nital
shuman hapeirot. It's the fatness of the fruit. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר הטהרה נטלה את הריח. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer hataharah natlah
et hare'ach.
The loss of purity has taken away the smell from the fruit.
המעשרות נטלו את השומן. Hama'asrot natlu et hashuman. The not doing sufficient
you know care with מעשרות ma'asrot has taken away the fatness of
the fruit. וחכמים אומרים. vachachamim omrim. We haven't reached this in the
גמרא? Gemara? Yeah. וחכמים אומרים
הזנות והכשפים כילו את הכל.
vachachamim omrim
haznut vehakshafim kilu et hakol. No, what really has completely corrupted society
is the sort of sexual impropriety and the witchcraft, going back to
the סוטה Sotah theme. Okay. So וממאי דמשבטלה סנהדרין. Umimai demishebatlah Sanhedrin.
Very cheery end of a מסכת. masechet. וממאי דמשבטלה סנהדרין. Umimai demishebatlah
Sanhedrin. How do we know that? כתיב. ketiv. How do we know
that verse about בשיר לא ישתו יין bashir lo yishtu yayin is
talking about when there's no סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע דאמר קרא. Amar Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua de'amar kra. The
verse says, זקנים משער שבתו בחורים מנגינתם. Zkeinim misha'ar shavatu bachurim minginatam.
The elders have ceased from their gates and the young men from
their singing. So the elders in their gates is the
בית דין. Beit Din. אמר רב. Amar Rav. אוזנא דשמעא זמרא תעקר.
Ozna d'shama zimra te'aker. So now we're talking you asked before descriptive
or prescriptive. Here seems more prescriptive. An ear nowadays that hears song
should be uprooted, like you know you should not be singing nowadays,
right? We should do it as a sense of mourning. Again, usually
we associate with the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, here connected to the
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin.
And instruments or just like singing?
Yeah so that's not being clear, right? I mean שיר shir but
זמר zemer could specifically true be with instruments. Right. Not being spelled
out here but good point. Could very well be that. אמר רבא.
Amar Rava. זמרא בביתא חורבא בסיפא. zimra beveita churba beseifa. If there
is singing or you might be right music in the household there
will be destruction by the by the porch by the what's it
called? Threshold. Thank you. שנאמר קול ישורר בחלון חרב בסף. shene'emar kol
yeshorer bachalon chorev basaf. If there's sound of the singing in the
in the window and destruction or the sword by the threshold.
כי ארזה ערה. Ki arzah eirah. מאי כי ארזה ערה? Mai ki
arzah eirah? אמר רבי יצחק. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak. בית המסובך בארזים. Bayit
hamisubach be'arazim. A house that was surrounded by cedars. עיר הוא? Ir
hu? Do you think that it is a city to be protected
from destruction? No. Even that will be destroyed. אלא אפילו בית המסובך
בארזים מתרועע. Ella afilu bayit hamisubach be'arazim mitro'eia. Again a different way
a play on the word ערה eirah מתרועע. mitro'eia. Will be shattered,
will be will be destroyed. אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. שמע
מינה כי מתחלי חורבא בסיפא מתחלי. shma mina ki matchali churba beseifa
matchali. When destruction begins it begins at the threshold שנאמר חרב בסף.
shene'emar chorev basaf. ואיבעית אימא מהכא ושאיה יוכת שער. Ve'iba'it eima mehacha
vesha'iyah yukat sha'ar. And the its destruction, its desolateness will be through
the gate. smitten
at the gate. So well that's where it'll be, sort of, laid
desolate. Another, by the way, that פסוק pasuk is also used in
another גמרא Gemara about how שדים shedim inhabit a house when it's
all left uninhabited. Okay, so רש״י Rashi says בית השער מעין יישוב
ובתוכה שעירים מרקדים שם ומרגיזים וחובטים את שעריו. Bayit hashaar mei'ein yishuv
uvetochah se'irim merakdim shamu umeratgzim vechovtim et she'arav. When it's laid desolate,
you know, the devils, the goat, the goats are the sort of
devil goats, you know, are, you know, take hold of it and
it destroys it. Okay, so where were we? Okay, יוכה שער. yukat
shaar. אמר מר בר רב אשי, Amar Mar bar Rav Ashi, לדידי
חזי לי. Lididi chazi li. Oh, this because of the next line
in the גמרא. Gemara. I saw something that type of a thing,
ומנגחי כטורין, umangchei katorin, they're goring
each other like
oxen.
Okay, אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, זימרא דנגדי ודבקרי שרי. Zimra
denagdei udevakrei shari. However, song that is done for like leading the
cattle, that's permissible because, you know, when they would sing to lead
the cattle, that would be done to for the purpose of their
work and to keep the cattle moving. So that's not a problematic
song, which by the way makes it sound like we're not דוקא
davka talking about musical instruments.
דגרדאי אסיר, Degarda'ei asir, but the one sung by the גרדאי, gardai,
which is what? I think it's tailors, right? Weavers, weavers is forbidden,
cause that's just סתם stam to entertain yourself and that's not necessary
for your work. Again, you take the simple sense of this גמרא,
Gemara, nobody can ever sing, right? Okay, רב הונא בטיל זימרא. Rav
Huna batil zimra. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to deal with that
problem. Okay, רב הונא Rav Huna tried to annul the song in
his community. Again, very much moving from the descriptive to the prescriptive.
קם מאה אווזי בזוזא ומאה סאוי חיטי בזוזא ולא יבעי. Kam mea
avzei bezuza umea sa'ei chiti bezuza velo iba'ei. So then it destroyed
any sense of joy of life, and you could buy, and the,
you know, a hundred geese were going for a זוז, zuz, and
a hundred, you know, bushels of wheat were going for a זוז,
zuz, and nobody wanted to buy it. Like what was the point?
Everything was, you know, everybody was so depressed. So אתא רב חסדא
זילזל ביה. Ata Rav Chisda zilzel beih. רב חסדא Rav Chisda came
and he like, you know, he disparaged this prohibition, you know, he
told people it's okay you can sing, maybe he sang himself. Okay,
he reversed it. ואיבעי אווזא בזוזא ולא משתכח. Ve'iba'ei avza bezuza velo
mishtakach.
And then the prices now took, it took a זוז zuz for
just one goose and you couldn't find it, everybody wanted it. So
everybody was now in a much better mood. Okay, so it's quite
an interesting גמרא, Gemara, right? We're supposed to be really depressed now,
there's no בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, no סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, but we do
have to sort of go on with life. אמר רב יוסף. Amar
Rav Yosef. Extremely confident.
There you go. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, זימרי גברי ועני
נשי. Zimrei gavrei ve'anei nashei. Now getting back a little to a
סוטה Sotah theme maybe. This actually, this next גמרא Gemara is quoted
a lot in different הלכה halacha contexts. If men are singing and
women are responding, so there's a responsive singing men and women, פריצותא,
pritzuta, that's general sexual looseness. But זימרי נשי ועני גברי, Zimrei nashei
ve'anei gavrei, but if it's the reverse, if the women are singing
and the men are doing the responding, so then they have to
listen much more closely, right, for their cue. So they're, you know,
they're much more focusing on the women and their singing. In that
case, כאש בנעורת. ke'esh bene'oret. That's like fire and flax. That's much
more combustible and potentially leads to real sin. למאי נפקא מינה? Lema'i
nafka mina? The גמרא Gemara says, what difference does it make? They're
both wrong. So it says, לבטולי האי מקמי האי. levatulei hai mikamei
hai. To tell you that if, it's fascinating, going back exactly to
the line before. Not everything that's wrong in society will we succeed
in being able to stamp down on, right? To stamp down on,
right? Something, so therefore if you have an ability like this is
going on and you can only get rid of one of them,
so this is the one to focus on is the second one.
Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. כל השותה בארבעה מיני זמר
מביא חמש פורעניות לעולם. Kol hashoteh be'arba'ah minei zemer meivi chamesh puraniyot
la'olam. If you drink, you know, again, now this some want to
limit, as Michael was saying, the problem of the song to musical,
live music. Someone limit it דוקא davka to drinking with the music.
So if you drink with music and four types of music, you
will get, you will bring about five punishments. שנאמר, Shene'emar, והיה כינור
ונבל
תוף וחליל ויין משתיהם,
vehaya kinor
vanevel
tof vachalil veyayin mishteihem, right? Like, you know...
Right, we're not talking about religious song. Right.
No, but also like, you know, the same this, like
weddings even, or...
well I don't know, whatever, it's all discussed in the פוסקים. poskim.
Okay, as you can see in the גמרא, Gemara, how much are
you really able to achieve this is also a challenge. הוי משכימי
בבוקר
שכר ירדופו. Hoy mashkimei vaboker shechar yirdofu. Woe to those who get
up early in the morning and run after mead, beer. מאחרי בנשף
יין ידליקם, Me'acharei vaneshef yayin yadlikem, and stay late at night wine
fires them up. והיה כינור ונבל תוף וחליל ויין משתיהם. Vehaya kinor
vanevel tof vachalil veyayin mishteihem. And it was all these musical instruments,
I don't know what they are. כינור Kinor is what? A lute,
which is, right, who knows what was כינור, kinor, a harp? A
harp. What's a נבל? nevel? A lyre? A lyre, what's a lyre?
A type of a harp? Harp? Yeah. Okay, a תוף tof is
a cymbal and a חליל chalil is a, is a flute, a
wind instrument, right? Okay, ויין משתיהם. veyayin mishteihem. So anyway, they have
all this music. And before here... right, and they're before, and wine
is their drink, ואת פועל השם לא יביטו, ve'et po'al Hashem lo
yabitu, and they do not see the acts of God. By the
way, it does not say... The only problem here is that they're
listening to music. Right? It seems like they've got a lot more.
They're getting drunk, they're waking up early in the morning, go to
bed late at night, just running after their wine. Okay, so again,
מה כתיב אחריו? Mah ketiv achrav? What does it say afterwards? לכן
גלה עמי מבלי דעת Lachen gala ami mibli da'at and it causes
the nation to go into exile, שגורמים גלות לעולם, she-gormim galut la-olam,
it causes exile to the world. וכבודו מתי
רעב, U-kevodo metei ra'av, שמביאים רעב לעולם, she-mevi'im ra'av la-olam, and it
brings, you know, famine to the world. והמונו צחה צמא Va-hamono tzecheih
tzamah is, you know, thirsty and parched, שגורמים לתורה, she-gormim la-Torah, now
here we're reading this metaphorically, שתשתכח מלומדיה, she-tishtakach mi-lomdeiha, because Torah is
water, so people forget Torah. וישח
אדם וישפל איש Va-yishach adam va-yishpel ish and a person is brought
low, שגורמים שפלות לשונאו של הקדוש ברוך הוא, she-gormim shiflut le-son'o shel
Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, even to the quote-unquote enemy of God, to God
essentially, it even brings God down. ואין איש אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא
Ve-ein ish ela Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu שנאמר ה' איש מלחמה. she-ne'emar Hashem
ish milchama. ועיני גבוהים תשפלנה Ve-einei gevohim tishpalna and the eyes of
those that are high is brought low, שגורמים שפלות של ישראל, she-gormim
shiflut shel Yisrael, it brings down Israel. ומה כתיב אחריו, U-mah ketiv
achrav, what does it say afterwards? לכן
הרחיבה
שאול נפשה, Lachen hirchiva she'ol nafsha, she'ol like the depths have opened
up its mouth, ופערה פיה לבלי חוק u-fa'ara piha livli chok and
yawned open its mouth without end. וירד הדרה והמונה ושאונה
ועלז בה. Va-yarad hadarah va-hamonah u-she'onah ve-aleiz bah.
Okay, and all of the glory goes down into the depths and
it rejoices with it. Fine. Very, very inspiring. Okay. Alright, so anyway,
really bad if you are, if you do all of this singing
and whatever. Again, the question is, really just singing? I mean, you
know, the פסוקים pesukim were talking about stuff that was a little
bit more radical than that and we are left with this question
about how much of this is really meant להלכה le-halacha and in
what context. Alright, משמתו mishematei anyway, but that was an interesting גמרא
Gemara that it did shift from descriptive to prescriptive.
Wait, this is one of the main sources that get quoted by
the פוסקים? poskim?
Well, no, no, I didn't mean about, well, there are a number
of גמרות Gemaras about singing and music and so on. No, I
meant specifically the גמרא Gemara about the men and the women, about
the idea that you can't always get rid of everything and you
have to sometimes focus on what you can get rid of, also
discussions about קול אשה kol isha and so on. Okay, now,
משמתו נביאים הראשונים mishemateu nevi'im harishonim from the time the first נביאים
nevi'im died, there was no longer אורים ותומים. Urim Ve-Thummim. מן נביאים
ראשונים, Man nevi'im rishonim, who are these first נביאים? nevi'im? So אמר
רב הונא Amar Rav Huna זה דוד
ושלמה zeh David Ve-Shlomo ושמואל ושלמה. u-Shmuel ve-Shlomo. That was an interesting
order, some go to שמואל, דוד, ושלמה. Shmuel, David, ve-Shlomo.
Anyway, the thing is
that early, there's a, that early. So it doesn't mean that there
was no physical אורים ותומים Urim Ve-Thummim but it wasn't working after
them to give them the answer. ורב נחמן אמר Ve-Rav Nachman Amar
בימי דוד זימון סליק וזימון לא סליק. be-yemei David zimen solek ve-zimen
lo solek. Sometimes in the time of דוד David you would get
an answer from the אורים ותומים Urim Ve-Thummim and sometimes not. שהרי
שאל צדוק ועלתה לו, שאל אביתר ולא עלתה לו. She-harei sha'al Tzadok
ve-altah lo, sha'al Avyatar ve-lo altah lo. When צדוק Tzadok asked from
it, he was, got a response. When אביתר Avyatar did, he did
not. שנאמר
ויעל אביתר She-ne'emar va-ya'al Avyatar and אביתר Avyatar went up and again
רש"י Rashi sort of gives the context in the פסוקים, pesukim, but
it basically means that אביתר Avyatar got deposed from his position and
it's being read because that he was not able to give an
answer when דוד David asked from the אורים ותומים. Urim Ve-Thummim. When
דוד... שלמה... דוד David isn't a נביא? navi? He
says נביאים. nevi'im. Oh I see, that's good point, yeah, you're making
דוד David into a נביא. navi. It's a good point. Okay, yeah,
it's a good point. And we know he was in contact with
נביאים, nevi'im, but he wasn't, right, it's a good question. I don't
know how it's identifying him as a נביא. navi. Anyway, so because
that very, very early it stopped working which is also, which is
like man, like you know, as a but you know how, when,
when, when did things start going downhill? That's pretty early for things
to be going downhill. So the גמרא Gemara says מתיב רבה בר
שמואל Matvei Rabba bar Shmuel so we're going to switch this because
he asks from this, it says, ויהי לדרש אלוהים כל ימי זכריה
המבין בראות אלוהים, Va-yehi lidrosh Elokim kol yemei Zecharya ha-meivin bi-re'ot Elokim,
so it was there to ask from God all the days of
זכריה Zecharya who understood of the vision of God and that זכריה
Zecharya is the רש"י Rashi says it's the son of יהוידע, Yehoyada,
right, which is very, very late in the period of the, of
the kings. So it's quite late that the אורים ותומים Urim Ve-Thummim
was still working. המבין בראות אלוהים מאי לאו באורים ותומים? Ha-meivin bi-re'ot
Elokim mai lav be-Urim ve-Thummim? Does it not mean that they were
able to use the אורים ותומים Urim ve-Thummim till that late date?
לא, בנביאים. Lo, bi-nevi'im. No, they could ask the נביאים nevi'im what
God was saying but it didn't mean the אורים ותומים. Urim ve-Thummim.
תא שמע Ta shema let's, okay, let's try to prove it again
that it was much later. משחרב בית המקדש ראשון בטלו ערי מגרש
Mishecharav Beit Ha-Mikdash rishon batlu arei migrash from the time the first
בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash was destroyed there was no longer the cities
of the לויים Levi'im ופסקו אורים ותומים u-pasku Urim Ve-Thummim and the
אורים ותומים Urim Ve-Thummim stopped, so there you go, it's connected to
the end of the first בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. ופסק מלך מבית
דוד U-pasak melech mi-beit David and we lost a house, a kings
from the house of דוד, David, right, we had the חשמונאים Chashmonaim
but they weren't from the house of דוד. David. ואם ילחשך אדם
לומר Ve-im yelachashek adam lomar now if somebody whispers to you and
says ויאמר התרשתא להם אשר לא יאכלו מקודש הקודשים עד עמוד כהן
לאורים ותומים va-yomer ha-tirshata lahem asher lo yochlu mi-kodesh ha-kodashim ad amod
kohen le-Urim ve-Thummim as it says in the time of the בית
שני bayit sheini that you will not eat until the כהן kohen
arrives for the אורים ותומים Urim ve-Thummim which makes it sound like
that's going to happen maybe sometime
soon, אמור לו emor lo say no, that doesn't mean it's about
to happen, כאדם שאומר לחברו. ke-adam she-omer le-chavero. עד שיחיו מתים ויבוא
משיח בן
דוד. ad sheyichyu metim veyavo Mashiach ben David. אמן. Amen. So, when
משיח Mashiach comes, that's when it'll happen, okay? It doesn't mean it's
about to happen, it means the opposite. You see, even that line,
when משיח Mashiach comes, was already in the time of the גמרא.
Gemara. One minute, אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק ela amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak מנביאים ראשונים miviniim rishonim fine, you're right, it was
till the end of the בית ראשון. Bayit Rishon. So who are
the נביאים ראשונים? neviim rishonim? לפוקי lafokei from the very, very last
of the נביאים, neviim, חגי זכריה ומלאכי. Chaggai Zecharia uMalachi. Those are
the last three נביאים neviim and they were at the very beginning
of בית שני. Bayit Sheni. So at their stage, those end, the
very last נביאים, neviim, there was no longer a אורים ותומים. urim
vetumim. דאחרונים מיבעי ליה. deacharonim mibei leh. דתנו רבנן, detanu rabanan, משמתו
חגי זכריה ומלאכי, mishemetu Chaggai Zecharia uMalachi, when they, those three died,
נסתלקה רוח הקודש מישראל, nistalka ruach hakodesh miYisrael, there was no longer
a divine inspiration, רוח הקודש ruach hakodesh in Israel. So you see
those are the last of the נביאים. neviim. ואף על פי כן
veaf al pi chen and even so, היו משתמשים בבת קול. hayu
mishtamshim bebat kol. They would still be a heavenly voice that would
sometimes give them like a little bit of a message from heaven,
but it would not be a real רוח הקודש. ruach hakodesh. שפעם
אחת היו מסובים בעליית בית גוריא ביריחו, shepaam achat hayu mesubim bealiyat
beit Goria biYericho, once they were supping in—like that, I use supping
as a verb? Anyway, they were eating in the attic of בית
גוריא ביריחו, Beit Goria biYericho, נתנה להם בת קול מן השמים natna
lahem bat kol min hashamayim and a heavenly voice came from heaven
ואמרה veamra יש בכם אדם אחד שראוי שתשרה שכינה עליו, yesh bachem
adam echad sherauy shetishre Shechina alav, there's amongst you one person that
the divine presence should rest on him, which basically is showing not
only that there was a בת קול, bat kol, but also that
there was no נבואה nevuah because the בת קול bat kol was
saying one of you is deserving of נבואה nevuah but it can't
happen, okay? אלא
שאין דורו ראוי לכך, ela sheein doro rauy lekach, the generation is
not fit for it. נתנו עיניהם בהלל הזקן. natnu eineihem beHillel haZaken.
So they all looked at Hillel. They all knew that's who it
was talking about. וכשמת ukheshemat and when Hillel died,
הספידוהו hespiduhu הי חסיד הי עניו, hei chasid hei anav, woe to
the righteous, woe to the humble, תלמידו של עזרא, talmido shel Ezra,
a student of Ezra because again that's actually not in terms of
the
השראת שכינה hashraat shechina but עזרא הסופר Ezra haSofer in terms of
right, like being like the embodiment of תורה שבעל פה, Torah shebaal
peh, right, so the continuation of
תורה. Torah. ושוב פעם אחת היו מסובים בעלייה ביבנה, veshuv paam achat
hayu mesubim bealiya beYavne, another time they were doing this, ונתנה להם
בת קול מן השמים venatna lahem bat kol min hashamayim and a
heavenly voice came out of heaven. It's interesting, נתנה להם natna lahem
was given to them, a בת קול מן השמים. bat kol min
hashamayim. I should maybe here by the way is a good time
to point out that while in the בבלי Bavli בת קול bat
kol means a heavenly voice, Saul Lieberman, I forget, I have to
look at it again, but I think he's shown that in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi it more just means like a report, like there's a
שמועה shemuah that goes out, like it doesn't mean like a heavenly
voice. So נתנה להם בת קול מן השמים, natna lahem bat kol
min hashamayim, right, one wonders like did it mean they heard a
heavenly voice? Or they all had like some type of a, it's
sort of like divinely inspired to say this type of a thing?
How much is it something that was really experienced in a miraculous
type of a way?
Anyway, נתנה להם בת קול מן השמים, natna lahem bat kol min
hashamayim, a voice was given to them from heaven, ואמרה להם veamra
lahem and it said to them, יש בכם אדם אחד שראוי שתשרה
שכינה עליו, yesh bachem adam echad sherauy shetishre Shechina alav, another person
that's fit for the divine presence. So again, a בת קול bat
kol at the same time emphasizing the lack of נבואה. nevuah. אלא
שאין דורו זכאי לכך, ela sheein doro zakai lekach, but the generation
is not fit. נתנו עיניהם בשמואל הקטן. natnu eineihem biShmuel haKatan. They
looked at Shmuel who was a student of Hillel. וכשמת ukheshemat and
when he died, הספידוהו hespiduhu הי עניו הי חסיד, hei anav hei
chasid, again was they this very special הספד hesped apparently which was
only for the most righteous people. תלמידו של הלל. talmido shel Hillel.
So Hillel was a תלמיד talmid of Ezra, and Shmuel was a
תלמיד talmid of Hillel. ואף הוא אמר בשעת מיתתו, veaf hu amar
bishat mitato, and when he was and when he was dying he
said, שמעון וישמעאל לחרבא, Shimon veYishmael lecharba, Shimon and Yishmael will be
for destruction, so this was now the period of the
Hadrianic persecutions. So Shmuel I guess was not—no, if he was right
before the Hadrianic persecutions, Hadrianic persecutions were when? They were about 130...
135, right? So that's another, that's like 200 years after Hillel. So
that's about 200 years after Hillel, right? I would say so. Because
no, that's who they are, Shmuel and Yishmael... Shimon and Yishmael, are
Rabbi Shimon נשיא ישראל, Nasi Yisrael, Rabbi Yishmael בן אלישע, ben Elisha,
right, yeah, these are the עשרה הרוגי מלכות. asara harugei malchut. So
who was the שמואל הקטן Shmuel haKatan then? I don't know, I'm
not good at this. Who—does anybody, Charlie, does he—know who the שמואל
הקטן Shmuel haKatan is?
He's one of the תנאים, Tannaim, right?
Ah, was that the one?
He lived through the time of the destruction of the second Temple.
Oh, okay. Because he was the קטן, katan, that's what they had
him do because he was not, you know...
Right, right, right, okay. So תלמידו של הלל talmido shel Hillel is
the same way Hillel was a תלמיד talmid of Ezra. He wasn't
a literal תלמיד talmid of Hillel, he was like the
next continue—like spiritual disciple, exactly. Like the embodiment of תורה שבעל פה.
Torah shebaal peh.
Shimon and Yishmael were two of the ten martyrs.
Right, but that would have been after, but that would have been,
but that would have been a good 50 years after the חורבן.
churban. No, then
after. They—this would have been at the time of the destruction of
the Temple.
Oh yeah? It started at that time?
Because the ten martyrs are not in the same generation.
No, that I know, but I didn't realize how early it started.
Oh, okay fine. So that works. Okay. All right. So שמואל הקטן
Shmuel haKatan here, and thank you Michael for reminding me, right, he
was the one that composed the למלשינים. lamalshinim. למלשינים ברכה. LaMalshinim Bracha.
Okay, so he was a next—like, he was seen as a spiritual
descendant of הלל, Hillel, although הלל Hillel was a good, whatever, 150
years earlier, and—and this was when the persecutions began, time of the
חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayit. ואף הוא אמר בשעת מיתתו, Veaf Hu Amar
Bishat Mitato, שמעון וישמעאל, Shimon VeYishmael, you know, שמעון Shimon who was
the נשיא Nasi and ישמעאל Yishmael לחרבא Lecharva
they will be for destruction, they'll be martyred, וחברו לקטלא Vechavro Lektala
and their colleagues also will be slaughtered, ושאר עמא לביזא Usha'ar Ama
Leviza
and the rest of the nation will be for for being despoiled,
ועכאן סגיאין עתידין
למיתי על עמא Ve'akan Sagi'in Atidin Lemeti Al Ama and many travails
and suffering will occur to the people. ואף, Veaf, so that I
guess showing that he had a certain amount of you know of
heavenly inspiration. He wasn't a נביא, Navi, he didn't have רוח הקודש,
Ruach HaKodesh, but here you don't just have the בת קול, Bat
Kol, you actually have a little bit of a fulfillment of the
ראוי שתשרה שכינה, Ra'uy SheTishre Shechina, a little divine inspiration. ואף על
רבי יהודה בן בבא ביקשו לומר הי חסיד הי עניו Veaf Al
Rabi Yehuda Ben Bava Bikshu Lomar Hei Chasid Hei Anav and even
for רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabi Yehuda Ben Bava they wanted to
see this, אלא שנטרפה השעה Ela SheNitrefa HaSha'ah but the the time
was was taken the opportunity was lost, שאין מספידין על הרוגי מלכות
SheEin Maspidin Al Harugei Malchut because since he was executed, he was
one of the הרוגי מלכות, Harugei Malchut, the martyrs, so they did
not want to sort of eulogize him because then they would have
gotten in trouble with the government. Tell you wanted to say something.
Yeah, back when they talk about אורים ותומים Urim VeTumim and the
priest studying קדשי הקדשים? Kadshei HaKadashim? Yep. That was about the priest
whose lineage was certain and they wanted to use the אורים ותומים
Urim VeTumim to be able to address that question.
I see. So maybe that had to do with why it wasn't
working. Okay. משחרב בית המקדש, Mishecharav Beit HaMikdash, בטל השמיר, Batal HaShamir,
when the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed the שמיר, Shamir, this
worm, was you know went lost.
Okay, so תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, שמיר שבו בנה שלמה בית המקדש
Shamir Shebo Bana Shlomo Beit HaMikdash and it says, והבית בהבנותו אבן
שלמה מסע נבנה, VehaBayit Behibanoto Even Shlemah Masa Nivnah,
it was a full stone, okay, it was built by the full
stone being carried from the quarry. So הדברים ככתבן דברי רבי יהודה.
HaDevarim Kichtavan Divrei Rabi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda said literally they
would not use any metal to you know to sort of carve
it, they would just bang it out from the quarry and bring
it full. אמר לו רבי נחמיה, Amar Lo Rabi Nechemya, so they
would have to use the שמיר Shamir to smooth out its edges.
אמר לו רבי נחמיה וכי אפשר לומר כן, Amar Lo Rabi Nechemya
Vachi Efshar Lomar Kein, can you really say that? והלא כבר נאמר,
Vehalo Kevar Ne'emar, כל אלה אבנים יקרות, Kol Eleh Avanim Yekarot,
all of these are very weighty stones, מגוררות במגירה, Megurorot BaMegeirah,
they are like carved with a or you know hewn with a
whatever a מגירה Megeirah is, some type of a hewing vessel.
Anyway, it's a metal vessel. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר לא נשמע
בבית בהבנותו? Im Kein Mah Talmud Lomar Lo Nishma BaBayit Behibanoto? So
what does it mean that they did not hear any metal vessel
in the בית Bayit when it was being built? שהיה מתקין מבחוץ
ומכניס מבפנים. Shehaya Matkin Mibachutz Umachnis Mibifnim. There's ways you don't hear,
you fix it on the outside, you don't bring it into the
you know you do whatever you need before you bring it to
the actual location.
And you really didn't see that, you didn't see metal for any
of this? Right. Well, that's what that's
going to be the גמרא's Gemara question exactly. Exactly, construction. Okay, anyway,
so the point is the idea of not using any metal vessels,
according to him, was just on site you don't use any metal
vessels, but you use them before you bring the stuff. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב ניחא דברי רבי יהודה, Amar Rav Nicha
Divrei Rabi Yehuda, so he wants to make he wants to sort
of make a פשרה Pesharah באבני מקדש. Be'avnei Mikdash.
I'd rather say like רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda that they didn't use
any metal vessels with the stones that they used for the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. ודברי רבי נחמיה, Vedivrei Rabi Nechemya, and רבי נחמיה
Rabi Nechemya said they used metal vessels but off-site, באבני ביתו, Be'avnei
Beito, the stones that they used for שלמה's Shlomo house, which is
okay, שלמה's Shlomo house, for the palace. I mean, but okay, big
deal. Anyway, ולרבי נחמיה, Ulerabi Nechemya, now according to רבי נחמיה Rabi
Nechemya that they were able to use metal vessels off-site, שמיר למה
לי? Shamir Lama Li? Who needed a שמיר? Shamir? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא,
Miba'ei Lei Lecheditanya, like we taught, אבנים הללו, Avanim Halalu, these stones,
the stones for the אפוד, Efod, אין כותבין אותן בדיו, Ein Kotvin
Otam Bediyo, where you had to write the 12 names of the
12 tribes,
you don't just put the names of the tribes on with ink
on the stone, משום שנאמר פתוחי חותם Mishum Shene'emar Pituchei Chotam because
it says basically carved, ואין משרטין עליהם באזמל Ve'ein Mesartin Aleihem Be'izmel
but you don't use an awl to carve into them, משום שנאמר
במלואותם Mishum Shene'emar Bimluotam because it said they have to be full,
they can't actually be missing anything. אלא, Ela, which is again also
funny because you know even to get them the right size, you
obviously have to carve them, you know they don't come out of
the ground exactly whatever size you're going to use them in the
in the אבני אפוד, Avnei Efod, but okay, anyway. Right, אלא, Ela,
right, אלא כותב עליהם בדיו, Ela Kotev Aleihem Bediyo,
you write with ink, ומראה להם שמיר Umar'eh Lahem Shamir and you
show the you show them to the שמיר Shamir מבחוץ Mibachutz and
I guess the שמיר Shamir follows by follows the the path of
the ink, והן נבקעות מאליהן Vehen Nivka'ot Me'aleihen and as the שמיר
Shamir goes on them they crack where the שמיר Shamir was, כתאינה
זו שנבקעה בימות החמה Kite'einah Zu Shenivke'ah Bimot HaChama like this
like this fig that crack you know that that splits in the
summer, ואינה חסרה כלום Ve'einah Chasera Kelum but nothing is missing, something
can crack open but if it cracks open naturally you're not going
to be losing any of the material. Okay, וכבקעה זו שנבקעה בימות
הגשמים Uchevik'ah Zu Shenivke'ah Bimot HaGeshamim or like a you know a
valley
like a a crevice in the ground that opens up in the
rain season.
ומששת ימי בראשית נברא u’misheshat yemei bereishit nivra and it’s born
and it’s created from the six days of creation. I don’t understand
that, doesn’t everything come originally from the six days of creation?
Well, it would be the בין השמשות, bein hashemashot, right? בין השמשות.
bein hashemashot. Pirkei Avot?
Okay, that’s what it means. Anyway, okay. ואין כל דבר קשה יכול
לעמוד בפניו, ve'ein kol davar kashe yakhol la'amod befanav,
but it doesn’t mean that it’s the same one from then because
it says it’s created from the barley seed. Anyway, does it mean
that there's only one of them? I don't know.
Anyway, it was created during the Sabbath eve
twilight.
Okay, what's to do the בין השמשות? bein hashemashot? But as the
other point that also that it’s whatever, that there’s only one of
them? Anyway, ואין כל דבר קשה יכול לעמוד בפניו, ve'ein kol davar
kashe yakhol la'amod befanav, nothing nothing strong can stand before it. במה
משמרין אותו, bameh meshamerin oto, so what do you keep it in?
Because if nothing can stand before it, what do you keep it,
whatever you're going to keep it in, it’s going to burn its
way out of. Okay, so eat its way out. No, I thought
it meant that it lets like some type of a left an
acid trail is what I was that’s what I was assuming because
then it goes down on the follows things like an acid.
I forget what it’s called exactly that you have to keep it
in wax because it won’t eat through wax.
Really? So that’s the same idea here. So if this exudes an
acid, what do you keep it in? Okay. כורכין אותו בספוגין של
צמר, korkhin oto bisfogin shel tzemer, so similar point to like the
irony that you use something soft. So you use wool, okay, wrap
it in wool, ומניחין אותו באיתני של אבר. uminichin oto be'itani shel
avar. איתני itani I think is like some type of a tube
probably of lead. Right, it’s like kryptonite. מלאה סובי שעורין mele'ah suvei
se'orin
filled, here we get barley again, filled with like the the the
bran of barley. אמר רב אמי, Amar Rav Ami, משחרב מקדש ראשון
בטלה שירה פרנדה mishecharav mikdash rishon batla shira paranda וזכוכית לבנה. uzkhukhit
levana.
So so we from the time of the first בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash we lost the this very fine silk and white clear glass.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hakhi, we taught similarly, משחרב מקדש ראשון
בטלה שירה פנדא mishecharav mikdash rishon batla shira panda וזכוכית לבנה uzkhukhit
levana ורכב ברזל, verekhev barzel, we also lost iron chariot, which is
interesting. ויש אומרים אף יין קרוש הבא משניר הדומה כעיגולי דבלה, ve'yesh
omrim af yayin karush haba mi'shanir hadomeh ke'igulei dveila,
even the type of a congealed wine that we got from שניר
Shanir which is like these these what do you call it like
these pressed rounds of of figs, you know, so the wine would
come nice and congealed, I guess, and then you could like use
a little bit and put water add water to it. It was
the first, you know, like instant type of wine or something. Okay,
so anyway, those are some of the things we lost. ונופת צופים,
Venofet Tzufim, we also lost נופת צופים. nofet tzufim. What is this?
מאי נופת צופים? mai nofet tzufim? אמר רב, Amar Rav, סולת שצפה
על גבי נפה. solet shetzafa al gabei nafa.
So where you had a type of a fine flour that was
so rich or sweet or whatever, it would get adhere to the
top of the sieve and it wouldn’t go down the sieve.
ודומה לעיסה שנילושה בדבש vedomeh le'isa shenilosha bidvash ושמן, vashemen, and oil.
ולוי אמר, VeLevi amar, שתי ככרות הנדבקות בתנור. shtei kikkarot hanidbakot batanur.
No, what you would it
would what used to be is you would used to put two
loaves as Rashi says at opposite walls in the oven, ותופחין ובאות
עד שמגיעות זו לזו, vetofkhin u'va'ot ad shemagi'ot zo lazo, and they
would expand so much that they would fill the oven and they
would touch each other in the middle of the oven.
It was since the original blessing the dough.
Yeah, there's no blessing in the bread, right, exactly. ורבי יהושע בן
לוי
אמר, VeRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amar, זה דבש הבא מן הציפה zeh
dvash haba min hatzipa or מן הצופים, min hatzufim, some say honey
that comes from צופים Tzufim from these mountains, you know, like we
have הר הצופים. Har HaTzufim. מאי משמע, Mai mashma, where do you
see that נופת nofet sort of means that? כדמתרגם רב ששת, ked'metargem
Rav Sheshet, this is on the פסוק pasuk that says כאשר תעשינה
הדבורים, ka'asher ta'asena hadvorim, like the like the bees will do. So
he his translation is כמא דניצן דביאתא ושייטן ברומא עלמא, kema denitzan
devyata veshaitan beruma alma, like the like the bees sort of fly
up in the heights of the heaven,
ומסקן דובשא מעשבי טורא, umaskan duvsha me'isbei tura, and they bring honey
from the grass of the mountain. So you see that honey the
good honey comes from the mountains, so נופת, nofet, a נופת nofet
is like dripping and צופים tzufim here is being read as the
mountain the high mountains. Wildflower. Wildflower honey, there you go. ותנן התם,
U'tnan hatam, we taught over there, כל הניצוק טהור, kol hanitzok tahor,
since we’re talking about honey,
כל הניצוק טהור, kol hanitzok tahor, anything that is poured is is
טהור, tahor, meaning if you pour from a vessel into a טמא
tamei vessel, the stuff that’s left behind in the other vessel is
טהור tahor even though it’s connected through the pouring. חוץ מדבש זיפים
והצפיחים, chutz midvash zifim vehatzapichin,
except for honey of זיפים Zifim and צפיחים, tzapichin, I believe they’re
actual cakes of honey. That’s so thick that that’s like a solid,
that’s like one unit. So if the bottom becomes טמא, tamei, the
top becomes טמא. tamei. מאי זיפים, Mai Zifim, what is זיפים? Zifim?
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, דבש שמזייפין בו. dvash shemezayefin bo.
Rashi says the honey is so good you can mix it with
other things and nobody will notice because the power is so strong,
so it allows you to sort of like, you know, cutting your
honey. So anyway, ריש לקיש אמר, Resh Lakish amar, על שם מקומו,
al shem mekomo, no, that’s a place. כדכתיב, ked'khitiv, זיף וטלם ובעלות.
Zif v'Telem u'Ve'alot. וכיוצא בו. ve'khayotzei vo. וכיוצא בדבר אתה אומר u-k’yozei
badavar ata omer בבוא הזיפים b’vo ha-Zifim when the זיפים Zifim came
ויאמרו לשאול הלא דוד v’yamru l’Shaul halo David and said to שאול
Shaul etcetera. מאי זיפים? Mai Zifim? אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan
בני אדם המזייפים דבריהם, bnei adam ham’zaifim divreihem, people who lie. ורבי
אלעזר אומר V’Rabbi Elazar omer על שם מקומם. al shem mekomam. No,
it’s a place. כדכתיב k’diktiv זיף וטלם ובעלות. Zif v’Telem u-Be’alot. Okay,
let’s read one more line. Look at that, we caught up. ופסקו
אנשי אמנה. u-pasku anshei amana. אמר רבי יצחק Amar Rabbi Yitzchak אלו
בני אדם שהן מאמינים בהקדוש ברוך הוא, elu bnei adam shehen ma’aminim
b’Hakadosh Baruch Hu, people who actually have faith in God. That stopped
by the דתניא d’tanya רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר Rabbi Eliezer ha-Gadol omer
כל מי שיש לו פת בסלו, kol mi she-yesh lo pat b’salo,
anybody that has bread in their basket ואומר מה אוכל למחר, v’omer
ma ochal l’machar, and says like, you’ve got stuff in your in
your pantry, for
what shall I eat tomorrow? אינו אלא מקטני אמנה. eino ela m’katnei
amana.
Says that’s somebody who lacks faith.
Very high level of faith they had at that time.
Right. והיינו דאמר רבי אלעזר v’hainu d’amar Rabbi Elazar מאי דכתיב, mai
d’chtiv, what’s meant כי מי בז ליום קטנות? ki mi vaz l’yom
katanot? מי גרם, mi garam, who is you
know despises a day of smallness? מי גרם לצדיקים שיתבזבז שולחנם לעתיד
לבוא? mi garam l’tzadikim she-yitbazbez shulchanam l’atid lavo?
What led the righteous that their table will be despised in the
world to come, that they won’t have everything they deserve in the
world to come? קטנות שהיה בהן. katanut she-hayah bahen. The smallness that
they have. Even the צדיקים tzadikim nowadays, that they are not they
don’t have full אמונה. emunah. שלא האמינו בהקדוש ברוך הוא. she-lo he’eminu
b’Hakadosh Baruch Hu. They don’t have full faith in God that God
will provide for them. So because they’re worried about what they’re going
to have to eat the next day in this world and they
don’t have full faith in God, their table again it’s a similar
like מידה כנגד מידה mida k’neged mida will not be full in
the world to come. Okay, we will end with this for now.
See you all tomorrow.